<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The marks of the true church the virgin &amp; spouse of Christ that brings forth by a holy seed the birth that pleaseth God, and the marks of the false church, or whore, that brings forth by an evil seed the cursed birth that never could please God / by Morgan Watkins.</title>
            <author>Watkins, Morgan, fl. 1653-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09418486</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09418486</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43044</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43044)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1319:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The marks of the true church the virgin &amp; spouse of Christ that brings forth by a holy seed the birth that pleaseth God, and the marks of the false church, or whore, that brings forth by an evil seed the cursed birth that never could please God / by Morgan Watkins.</title>
                  <author>Watkins, Morgan, fl. 1653-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The prophecy of John Hus, prophesying the reformation of the church"--p. 27.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church --  Biblical teaching.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43044:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43044:1"/>
            <p>THE MARKS OF THE True Church, THE Virgin &amp; Spouſe of Chriſt, that brings forth by a Holy Seed the Birth that pleaſeth GOD. And the MARKS of the <hi>Falſe Church,</hi> or Whore, that brings forth by an Evil Seed, the Curſed Birth, that never could pleaſe God. Signified by a <hi>Voice from the Word of Life,</hi> or a Certain Sound of the Trumpet that hath awakened Thouſands, that were aſleep in the Night of thick Darkneſs and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, who are come to the Judgment of the Truth, that redeems out of BABYLON, and brings to SION. By which all are Summoned that are yet afar off, to appear before, and ſtand to the Judgment of the Ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Word in their Hearts, that by it they may know, What they are joyned to. <hi>By</hi> Morgan Watkins.</p>
            <q>What, know ye not that he which is joyned to an Harlot is one Body? for two (ſaith he) ſhall be one Fleſh: But he that is joyned unto the Lord is one Spirit,
<bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 6.16, 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:43044:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43044:2"/>
               <head>The <hi>MARKS</hi> of the <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH,</hi> the Virgin and Spouſe of Chriſt, that brings forth by a Holy Seed, the Birth that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God.</head>
               <p n="1">I. THey are ſuch, who are turned from Darkneſs unto Chriſt the true Light, that ſhines in their Hearts, who believe and walk in it, and are turned from the Power of Satan unto the Power of God, that they receive (in Chriſt the Light) to become his Sons, <hi>having Redemption through his Blood. the Forgiveneſs of Sin,</hi> and Sanctification in and by that Life that is the Light of Men, <hi>and made Partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Such who have received the Word in a Meaſure, that ſpake in the Prophets, by which they propheſied, and was their Foundation, which the Apoſtles were Miniſters and Preachers of, and was their Foundation, which they turned the People to, and they that believed, it was their Foundation; and they that believe and have received the Truth now, it is their Foundation and the Rock in all Ages; <hi>For other Foundation can no Man lay then that is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.11. God's Foundation that he hath laid for the Salvation of every Man, which is the <hi>Word grafted in them, that is able to ſave the Souls of all that receive it.</hi> Jam. 1.21. But they that reject it periſh, and are but the Chaff that the Wind blows to and fro.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Such who are in the Unity of the Spirit of Truth, and the Righteouſneſs which is of Faith; that ſaith, <hi>The Word, is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43044:3"/>nigh thee, in thy Mouth and in thy Heart, that is the Word of Faith</hi> (that Faith comes by the Hearing of) and the Word which the Apoſtles preached, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 8.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Unfeigned Love to God and to the Brethren; <hi>By this ſhall all Men know</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that ye are my Diſciples, if ye have Love one to another,</hi> John 13, 35.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Such who are born again of <hi>Incorruptible Seed, by the Word of God, which liveth and abideth forever,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.23. And are renewed in the Spirit of their Minds, being <hi>by one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit all baptized into one Body, and have been all made to drink into one Spirit,</hi> by which they are quickned into one Life, which is the Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt, that comes down from Heaven, the Children's Bread (as Chriſt ſaith) <hi>He that eateth me, even he ſhall live by me,</hi> John 6.57. And this is the Life that brings forth Fruit of Righteouſneſs, and Birth of God that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the World, and is made manifeſt to that of God in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man's Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Such who make a good Confeſſion by giving up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſuffer for the Righteouſneſs ſake of the Kingdom of God, and do not deny him before Men, by a ſubjecting to their Wills, againſt the Requirings of the Spirit of God; but are made willing to drink of the Cup, and be baptized with the Baptiſm their Lord and Maſter was baptized with, patiently taking up his Croſs, contentedly bearing his Reproach, and continuing faithful to the Death.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Humility and ſelf Denyal, hating Covetouſneſs, Pricle, and the Pomp, vain Glory and Honour of this World, having the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, without Reſpect of Perſons; <hi>Not having Mens Perſons in Admiration becauſe of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, but doing Good unto all, eſpecially to the Houſhould of Faith;</hi> Viſiting the Sick and Impriſoned for Righteouſneſs ſake, <hi>the Fatherleſs and Widdows in their Affliction, keeping them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unſported from the World,</hi> Jam. 1.27.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:43044:3"/>
               <p n="8">VIII. Such who are Witneſſes of the Spirit's Confeſſion; that Chriſt is come in the Fleſh, and hath condemned Sin in it in the Hour of his Judgment, that the Body of Sin might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by him, that is come and received, <hi>To take away the Sin, and bring in the perfect Righteouſneſs,</hi> that being crucified with him, and ſo ſuffering with him in the Fleſh, dying with him (that is, by the Strength of his Power that overcomes Sin and Death) we come to be raiſed up with him (by the Power that raiſed him up) and ſo come to live to God (by him and in him) and no more to the Luſts of the Fleſh, but to the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Spirit and Power, that gives us Victory over Death, and raiſeth the Soul to Life, by the quickning Spirit, that gives us a Will, Deſire, Hunger, Power and Strength, to live to the Good Will and Pleaſure of our unutterable good and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, of whoſe Mercy and Goodneſs ſome feel more then Tongue of Man can declare; and God is Witneſs, ſuch would that all Men might feel the ſame; and God is haſtening his Work, that Thouſands of Thouſands may feel it, and ſing of it in the Glory of his Preſence for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">IX. Such who in their Meaſures witneſs the Reign of Sin and Death put down in them, with all its great Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, by which it reigned from <hi>Adam</hi> until <hi>Moſes,</hi> and doth ſtill in all that have not received the free Gift of Righteouſneſs (in which is God's Power revealed) and ſuch are pleading for the Reign and Law of Sin, and for the Body of Sin to live in them till they dye, becauſe they are under its Reign: But, as I have ſaid, The Members of the True Church witneſs him come, whoſe Right it is to reign in them; who, having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him (the Gift of God) hath and is putting down all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and all Rule that is not of God, nor ought to reign and rule in Man; ſo caſts out the Strong Man, and ſpoils all his Goods: And theſe know him in them [mark that] <hi>greater then he that is in the World;</hi> who hath caſt out the Prince of the World, and reigns over Death and Hell. And theſe are not looking for the Kingdom of Heaven to come with Outward Obſervations, as the Hypocrites did of old, and ſtill do, who look for the Reign of a Perſon without them, and know not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43044:4"/>that Hell and Death reigns in them (which ſome of late did know to their Sorrow, that others might be warned) who ſee not him that is inviſible (to the Carnal Eye) that is come and coming <hi>in the Ten Thouſands of his Saints to judge the World,</hi> and all the fallen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngels.</p>
               <p n="10">X. Such who are gathered (by the Spirit of the Lord) out of all Gatherings in the Fall, that ſtand in the Will and Wiſdom of Man; and theſe <hi>follow Chriſt, the Shepherd and Biſhop of their Souls,</hi> and abide in his Doctrine and Spiritual Worſhip, and cannot hearken to a Stranger, who is made a Miniſter or a Biſhop in the Will of Man, and not made by the Holy Ghoſt an Overſeer of the Soul, but are climbed up another Way, and not come in through Chriſt the Door, by the Gift of his Spirit, but in the Wiſdom of Man, and of the Birth of the Fleſh that perſecutes the Sheep for the Fleece, therefore the Sheep cannot hear them; for he that gives the Soul Eternal Life, the Soul ought to hear, and be ſubject to, and to all that come in his Name (that is, his Power) who feeds the Sheep &amp; Lambs with the Bread of Life, that is Meat indeed and Drink indeed, where the Word of Life miniſters through the Veſſel, the Sheep that are gathered by the Spirit, do know the Voice of the Spirit, which is the Voice of Chriſt, that the Stranger knows not; but the Sheep and their Souls are greatly refreſhed by that Miniſtry of Life, and ſo is the Body of Chriſt edified; but where the Gift of Life is not received, nothing but Death can preach, and that burdens, and hurts, and defiles the Soul if it be touched or fed upon; therefore in a Figure, he that touched the Dead was to be unclean by the <hi>Jews</hi> Law; ſo by the Law of the Spirit of Life, dead Works, that are Works of Darkneſs, the Living are to have no Fellowſhip with, but rather reprove them: So this is the Infallible Truth, that the Children of Truth and Sheep of Chriſt, will hear and obey none but the Voice of the Spirit of Chriſt, the Truth, the Light and the Life, which every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Body, hath a Meaſure of in himſelf, which is the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing that leads, guides, and teacheth all his to profit: in the Movings and Requirings of which, all may propheſie one by one, that all may be edified, and the whole Body built up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43044:4"/>in Love, a Habitation for the Lord to dwell in, to walk in, work in, and ſpeak in; and theſe have received Eternal Life (dwelling in it) ſhall never periſh.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. Such who have put off the Old Man with his vain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and have (in their Meaſure) <hi>Crucified the Fleſh with its Affections and Luſts, who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit,</hi> which is become their Leader (as ever it was their Fathers Children) in which they find Power to do the Will of God in Earth, as in Heaven; <hi>Being created again after the New Man in Righteouſneſs and True Holineſs,</hi> and being become New Creatures, are in Covenant with God; Old Things are paſt and paſſing away, and becoming and become New; a clean Heart and a right Spirit poſſeſſeth the Body, which <hi>loves the Lord wholy, and his Neighbour and Brother as himſelf;</hi> true Judgment and Juſtice ſits in his Gate, and Goodneſs, Mercy, and Love within his Houſe; his <hi>Law is come forth of</hi> Sion, <hi>and the Word of his God from</hi> Jeruſalem; in the Doctrine of which he abides, and Statutes and Ordinances keeps, who ſwears not at all, nor lyes; for that is againſt the Truth, and under Condemnation; who is come to the End of Wars and Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and <hi>doth to all as he would be done unto,</hi> that ends Swearing, Lying, Fighting and Luſting after Evil Things, loves Enemies, ſerves Friends, reſpects not Perſons, but gives to all their Due, <hi>To</hi> Caeſar <hi>the Things that are his, and to God the things that are his;</hi> labours in Love for the Good of all, and doth Good to all; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes to hold up the Types and Shadows under the changeable Prieſthood (which are fulfilled in the unchangeable) that point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Chriſt and his good Things; who ends the Old Things, the Old Prieſthood, and the Law that upheld it; and Chriſt, the Everlaſting Prieſt, being come, the Subſtance of them all, cannot deny him before Men, by holding up the Old Things that he hath aboliſhed by his Coming, which, if now upheld, were to deny Chriſt come in the Fleſh, <hi>the High-Prieſt of our Profeſſion,</hi> Heb. 3.1. Now if we profeſs him to be our High Prieſt, and hold up another Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, by paying of Tythes, and other Things abrogated and denyed by the Holy Brethren of the Heavenly Calling in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43044:5"/>Dayes: I ſay then, though we do profeſs him in Words to be come, yet we ſhould deny him in Works, and ſo do all that hold up the Ceremonies now the Subſtance is come, who is <hi>a merciful and faithful High Prieſt in Things appertaining to God, to make Reconciliation for the Sins of the People,</hi> Heb. 2.17. And thoſe that hold up or eſtabliſh another Righteouſneſs, fall ſhort of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt; <hi>Seeing then that we have a great High Prieſt, that is paſſed into the Heavens, Jeſus, the Son of God, let us hold faſt our Profeſſion,</hi> Heb. 4.14. Which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſtands in Chriſt, the better Hope, by the which we draw nigh to God, whoſe Kingdom is not of this VVorld, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the King, Put up the Sword, and know that Nature that could kill with the Sword Outward, to be ſlain with the Sword Inward; for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this World, if my Kingdom were of this World, then would my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants fight,</hi> John 18.36. Then all you that fight, conſider whoſe Servants you are, ſeeing Chriſt's Servants cannot; ſo all theſe Things forbidden, are not to be uſed by the Children of God's Kingdom, and Inheritors of the New Covenant, in which the New Man enjoyes all the Promiſes of God, that are Yea and Amen to him forever.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. As to the Miniſtry, they are ſuch that the Lord of the Harveſt fitteth by his Spirit, and ſends into the Harveſt, being <hi>called and choſen,</hi> to be faithful Labourers in God's Harveſt, and are content with his Wages (and refuſe Anti chriſt's) having freely received, do freely give, according to their Maſter's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, who warch for the Souls Good (and not for the Fleece) having Food and Raiment are contented, and are to be ready to do the Maſters Will in all Things, and go whither the Spirit requires them, and to preach the Word of Truth he gives them, not conſulting with Fleſh and Blood, but with Chriſt revealed in them, who teacheth them to profit the People, and to divide the Word aright, with Boldneſs, not fearing Man, nor the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Darkneſs, but to ſhew the People their Sin, that they that are yet in it, may come to repent, and amend their Lives, by turning from Darkneſs to the Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God, by receiving the Troth, in which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43044:5"/>is found Power to do it, and then they do the Things they ought ought to do, and leave undone the Things they ought not to do, and ſo calling upon the Name of the Lord (whom they ſerve and obey) he anſwereth them, and gives them more Grace, more Strength, more Power to rule over much, becauſe they are faithful in a little; and this is the profiting by the Gift, <hi>the Manifeſtation of the Spirit, that is given to every Man to profit withal;</hi> without which there is no profiting nor pleaſing God: And this Miniſtry that comes in the Name of the Lord, but few will hear, becauſe he comes with the Sword of the Spirit to ſlay that Life that lives in the fleſhly Luſts, that wars againſt the Soul; but they that do hear him that comes in the Name of the Lord, they do hear the Lord, who ſaith, <hi>Hear, and your Souls ſhall live;</hi> that is, who do obey the Voice of the Lord, they receive Power to become, the Sons of God; but he that is not ſent of God, may have the Words, but not having received the Word, hath but his Dream and the Words to tell, who comes in his own Name, that is, his own Power and Wiſdom; and the People being in the ſame, hear him, and receive his Doctrine, becauſe he ſpares their Life of Pleaſure in the Fleſh, and makes them believe they ſhall receive a Life of Glory af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Death (and that is his Dream he tells for Money) and ſo deceives the Soul, and keeps it in Death, ſerving the Luſt, and ſo the Sin, yet perſwading themſelves, by the Help of the Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that they ſerve the Lord; <hi>But no Man</hi> (ſaith Chrſt) <hi>can ſerve two Maſters,</hi> eſpecially whoſe Wayes are ſo contrary one to the other; and ſo being taught to confeſs him in Words, but deny him in Deeds, drawing nigh with their Mouthes, but the Heart is after other Lovers, <hi>theſe having at moſt but a Form of Godlineſs, but denying the Power thereof;</hi> Theſe the Children of Truth deny and turn from, therefore are hated and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them, whoſe falſe Religion they deny, who themſelves ſhew it to be falſe by their perſecuting Spirit, that is of <hi>Cain;</hi> for <hi>Cain's</hi> Spirit can bring forth no other but <hi>Cain</hi>'s Religion; that ist a Worſhip and Sacrifice that is out of the Truth, that can never pleaſe God, nor ever will, but it ever pleaſed moſt Men, and ſo it doth now; but we can ſay, <hi>The Lord forgive
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43044:6"/>them, they know not what they do;</hi> and ſo we muſt drink of our Maſter's Cup, and be baptized with his Sufferings, and ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering with him, ſhall reign with him. World without End, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>MARKS</hi> of the <hi>FALSE CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH,</hi> or Whore, that brings forth by an Evil Seed, the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Birth, that never could pleaſe God.</head>
               <p n="1">I. SHE is made up of ſuch Members who walk in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and love Darkneſs rather then Light, becauſe their Deeds are Evil; <hi>For every one that doth Evil, hateth the Light, neither cometh to the Light,</hi> Joh. 3.20. Therefore it is clear, they that walk in Darkneſs, are Evil-doers, and Evil-doers are the Members of the falſe Church or Whore: <hi>For if any that walk in Darkneſs ſay they</hi> (are Members of the Church of Chriſt, and) <hi>have not Fellowſhip with him, they lye, and do not the Truth,</hi> 1 John 1.6. And ſo all that cannot witneſs in Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure Darkneſs to be paſt, are ſtill in it, and Children of it.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Such who have not received the Word grafted in them, yet are profeſſing the Words, but will not come to the Word of Eternal Life, that gave forth the Words; and being aſtray from that, <hi>Err, not knowing the Scripture nor the Power of God,</hi> being out of the Faith of God's Elect that overcomes the Word, which Chriſt (the Word) is the Author and Finiſher of, and is <hi>a Myſtery held in a pure Conſcience;</hi> and whoſoever hath not this Faith, the Gates of Hell will prevail againſt him; and his Houſe not being built upon this Rock (Chriſt the Word of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43044:6"/>Life) in the Day of Tryal will be overturned, and great will be the Fall thereof; but the Foundation of God (for Salvation) ſtandeth ſure, that is the Ingrafted Word, that is able to ſave the Soul; that dwelt richly in the Children of God (in all Ages, and alſo in this Age) who were the Houſhould of Faith, Members of the Church in God.</p>
               <p n="3">III. To be of a Faith or Belief that is not in the Unity of the Spirit of Life but of that which Man is Author and Finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of; which he hath made and formed in the Houſe of his Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary of the Words and Confeſſions of the Saints in Light, and Children of God, that were in the Faith, of that they confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and witneſſed; and ſo in the Myſtery, that they which have only the Words of the Hiſtory cannot ſee, nor doth that reveal it to them.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Profeſſing Obedience to God and Chriſt in Words, but living in the Diſobedience of his Spirit, and ſo in Works deny him, doing the Things they ought not to do, and leaving the Things undone that they ought to do; theſe love not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but are in the World's Love, which is ſelfiſh and Enmity to God, from whence proceed the Luſts that war in the Members, the Fruits of the Fleſh, and being in the Fleſh, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe God.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Are ſuch, whoſe Head is a viſible Man without them who takes in and puts out in his own Will and Pleaſure; theſe chuſe rather to obey Man then God, and cannot ſuffer for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake, becauſe their Head is not Chriſt, the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Such in whom the Unregenerate Nature bears Rule, and the Seed of the Serpent is Head, and the Government of Chriſt is not ſet up within; but Death through the Luſts reigns, and captivates the Soul under it, that it lives not to God, nor brings forth Fruit of Righteouſneſs, but is the Tree that cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43044:7"/>the Ground, that will be hewn down, and caſt into the Fire.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Are ſuch, whoſe Weapons of their Warfare are not Spiritual, but Carnal; therefore the ſtrong Holds of Satan are ſtanding in them, who are Aliens and Strangers from the New Covenant, in which is no Fighter, Killer, Murtherer nor Envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Wicked Perſon, but the New Creation is witneſſed, in which dwelleth Righteouſneſs, the Sword turned into a Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhare, and the Spear into a pruning Hook, where War is learn'd no more.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Such who deſpiſe and neglect the Gift of God, the Light that ſhines in their Hearts, <hi>the Manifeſtation of the Spirit that is given to every Man to profit withal,</hi> without which none can pleaſe God, nor worſhip him, as I have ſaid, but are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Servants, out of the Way of God, in their own Way, the Way of Sinners, out of the Counſel of God's Spirit in the Counſel of the Ungodly Spirit, out of the Way of Light Life, in the Way of Death and Darkneſs, dead to God, but alive to the World, and in the Wickedneſs thereof.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. Such who are not turned to the Spirit of Truth, in which God is worſhipped, cannot worſhip him; but (as Chriſt ſaid) <hi>Ye worſhip ye know not what;</hi> ſuch Worſhippers are all that are aſtray from the Spirit of Truth, who are all falſe, from the riſing of the Sun to the going down of the ſame; for being out of the Spirit, out of the Truth, for the Spirit is Truth.</p>
               <p n="10">X. Such whoſe Principle and Belief is, <hi>That the Miniſterial Offices in the Church of Chriſt, are intailed to a Succeſſion of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, choſen in the Will of Man,</hi> as if Man were to ſend forth Labourers into the Lord's Vineyard, and the Lord engaged to accept their Choice; of ſuch ſaith the Lord, <hi>I have not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they ran,</hi> Jer. 23.21. It is the Lord of the Harveſt (as I have ſaid) that is to ſend forth Labourers into his Harveſt, and Man to accept the Lord's Choice, becauſe they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43044:7"/>come in his Name; and the Apoſtles prayed, and ſaid, <hi>Thou Lord which knoweſt the Hearts of all Men, ſhew whether of theſe two thou haſt choſen:</hi> So the Choſen of God will receive none but the Lord's Choice.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. Such who have a Form of Godlineſs, but denying the Power thereof, ever learning (of the Hireling, that will ever be paid for Teaching) but never able to bring them to the Knowledge of the Truth, becauſe he himſelf is aſtray from that which gives the Infallible Knowledge of it.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. Such who perſecute and deſtroy Mens Lives for their Religion; thus did <hi>Cain, who was of that Wicked One,</hi> and all that do ſo, are of him ſtill; for he that doth not Righteouſneſs but hateth his Brother, is manifeſt to be a Child of the Devil, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.10. And it was ever from the Beginning, the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous perſecuted the Righteous; and to be perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake, was ever an Infallible Mark of God's Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and to perſecute for Righteouſneſs ſake was ever an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Mark of the Children of the Wicked One: Let none miſtake me, I do not ſay, that all that are perſecuted, are the Children of God; for Men have ſuffered, and may be perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and not for the Righteouſneſs ſake of God's Kingdom, but for their own Righteouſneſs ſake, who in their blind Zeal and Self-Will, are labouring to ſet up their Idol, or falſe Way, in Oppoſition to others; and others in the ſame oppoſing them; and here is one in the Beaſtly Nature and Will, puſhing at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame; and they that can get moſt Power and Strength in the Earth, they tear and devour the others: <hi>And if a Man give his Body to be burnt, and all his Goods to the Poor,</hi> and yet may not be accepted of God; for the Life of all true Religion is Love <hi>(for God is Love)</hi> and where that is wanting, <hi>Though a Man may ſpeak with the Tongue of Men and Angels, 'tis all but as ſounding Braſs or a tinckling Cymbal;</hi> for indeed, pure Religion, ſprings from the Nature, Vertue and Operation of the pure Spirit of God, brought forth in that Man that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, and denyes his own Will, that the Will of the Divine Nature may be done, which is come, <hi>to be done in Earth, as it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43044:8"/>is in Heaven;</hi> and that is the Kingdom that all Men are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſeek, which whoſoever receives not as a little Child, can by no Means enter into it: And bleſſed are all thoſe that having received it, do ſuffer for its Righteouſneſs ſake: And it was ever, and ſtill is, the greateſt Blindneſs and Ignorance among the Sons of Men, to believe or think, that pure Religion is to be forced into by Perſecution; for this I declare, They that are of that Judgment, never knew what pure Religion was; but thoſe that will have People to come to pure Religion, muſt let the Light and Glory of their Religion ſhine forth before Men, that God's Works in them may be ſeen to others, that is, to do Good before all, and to all, even as the Son of God did upon Earth in his own Body, and now doth the ſame by his Spirit, in the Bodies of thoſe that receive him. <hi>He that ſaith, he abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in him, ought himſelf alſo to walk, even as he walked,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.6. For all ſuch that think they ought to compel People to their Religion, becauſe they think it is true, muſt alſo judge that their Spirit is Infallible, for if it may fail, then it ought not to be a Rule to the Souls of ohers, nor a Judge of another Man's Faith or Religion, nor of the Things of God; but the Truth is, where any Force or Compulſion is put upon the Conſciences of Men, that is an Infallible Sign of a Fallible and <hi>Anti-chriſtian</hi> Spirit; for the Infallible Spirit of God in the Holy Men, left no ſuch Rule nor Example, but commanded the contrary, ſaying, <hi>Let every Man be fully perſwaded</hi> (or fully aſſured) <hi>in his own Mind,</hi> Rom. 14.5. Again ſaith, <hi>So then every one of us ſhall give an Account of himſelf to God,</hi> Ver. 12. For in this Caſe, ſaith <hi>Paul, Haſt thou Faith? have it to thy ſelf.</hi> Then what hath any Man to do, to Lord it over another Man's Faith; ſeeing he that doubteth is damned (that is, condemned in himſelf) becauſe not done in Faith, it is Sin: And now you blind Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, that would compel all to fall down to your Idol or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Heavenly Things; can you give Men Faith to believe your Image hath Life, if not, do not you compel Men to ſin againſt their Conſciences, ſeeing <hi>what is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> Rom. 14.23. And the Devil is the Author of all Sin; and all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors for Righteouſneſs ſake, are his Subjects, in whom the Man of Sin is unrevealed, <hi>who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43044:8"/>all that is called God, or that is worſhipped, ſo that he as God</hi> (mark that's he that would rule over Men's Conſciences) <hi>ſitteth in tqe Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God</hi> (that is, by taking that Power to himſelf that God never gave to any Man, that is, to force or compel People to any Worſhip that is not of Faith, that is Sin; and God that made Heaven and Earth is not the Author of Sin; but it is the Man of Sin, whom the Lord of Life is <hi>Conſuming with the Spirit of his Mouth, and deſtroying with the Brightneſs of his Coming,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.3, 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Objection,</hi> But ſome may ſay, <hi>Did not Chriſt in the Parable ſay, Compel them to come in.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Bleſſed be the Lord, many do witneſs that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion (which is not Outward Force) that are come into his Houſe, and that is by the Power of his Love (wherein he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites the Poor, who receive the Goſpel) that hath conſtrained us to deny our ſelves, and take up his Daily Croſs, and follow him; for the Truth is to be received in the Love of it, and then it overcomes the Enmity of the Fleſhly Will, and covers with the Spirit and Life, the Wedding-Garment, that the Heavenly Gueſts at God's Feaſt have put on, that no Perſecutor ever knew on himſelf nor can be put it upon another: So they that compel, and they that are thus compelled, are both without a Wedding-Garment and not meet for the Marriage Feaſt: And again, the falſe Church that perſecutes, is gone from the ſound Doctrine of the Apoſtles, and cannot endure it: Now the Spirit of Truth, that miniſtred in the Apoſtles, hath opened the Mouthes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to miniſter, as they have freely received the Gift and ſound Doctrine of Truth; and the Teachers that were heaped up by them (that were gone from the Word) after their own Luſts, cannot endure the Doctrine of the Light that manifeſts their Deeds of Darkneſs, and that which the Apoſtles turned the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to, the Teachers heaped up in Mens Wills, turn the People from; and ſo turn Peoples Ears from the Truth, to give Ear unto Fables, the Imaginations of the Heart, that are gone after the Luſts; and this <hi>Paul</hi> did propheſie ſhould come to paſs (as hath been, and is fulfilled) ſaying, <hi>For the Time will come, when they will not endure ſound Doctrine, but after their own Luſts
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43044:9"/>ſhall they heap to themſelves Teachers, having Itching Ears, and they ſhall turn away their Ears from the Truth, and ſhall be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Fables,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.3, 4. Here was an Apoſtacy propheſied of, that in the Light is ſeen to be fulfilled in its Time.</p>
               <p>And now by the Brightneſs of the Riſing of the Son of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, that is the Day-ſpring from on high, that hath viſited us, and hath given Light to us that ſate in Darkneſs, and in the Shadow of Death, and hath guided our Feet into the Way of Peace; and the Light, ſown for the Righteous, Thou ands witneſs, Glory be to God on high for evermore: And the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Works of Darkneſs are denyed and reproved, which the Children of Light can have no Fellowſhip with, but are come out from them, in Obedience to the Heavenly Viſion the Voice from Heaven, that is the Trumpet that hath awakened Thouſands, which ſaith, <hi>Come out of her my People, come out of her, and partake not of her Sin, leſt ye partake of her Plagues:</hi> And now the Lord hath according to his Promiſe, in the latter Dayes, brought us a Way we did not know (out of her) and led us in Pathes we had not walked in; and this we can ſay that walk in the Light, if it were the laſt Words that we ſhould ſpeak upon the Earth, that the Way we are brought to walk in (and in which the Faithful do walk) is the Way that the God of Heaven hath brought us into; let all the Earth ſpeak what they will againſt it, God, that lives forever, will make it proſper to the Ends of the Earth, and the ſaved in this Nation, ſhall and do walk in it, and ſo ſhall <hi>the ſaved in all Nations,</hi> that is, in Chriſt the Light of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> as it is written; <hi>And the Lord God and the Lamb is the Light thereof:</hi> And all the rotten-Principle'd Men in all Nations ſhall not be able to ſtand before, nor abide the ſound Doctrine of the Word of Life, <hi>that is Juick and powerful, and a Diſcerner of the Thoughts and Intentions of the Heart,</hi> except they come to the Hour of his Judgment, and be judged as Men in the Fleſh, that they may be quickned by the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and live to God in the Spirit: And now being led out from among them (that are in the Filthineſs of the Fleſh) by the Spirit of the Lord, and touching no unclean Thing, the Lord hath received us, and is a bleſſed Father unto
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43044:9"/>his Sons and Daughters, that he hath begotten unto himſelf, by an Immortal Seed, the Word of Life, that liveth and abideth ſorever.</p>
               <p>And now thoſe pretended Fathers in God, who are called <hi>Lords Spiritual,</hi> which Title the Biſhops made by the Holy Ghoſt, Overſeers of the Flock of God, never received, not owned, nor ever will; and had you been our Fathers indeed, who had begotten us in God, we ſhould have been your moſt dear and dutiful Children, in all the Commands of Chriſt through you; but you know by whom you were made, but not by whom we are begotten; for if you did we believe you would not labour to deſtroy us, as ſome of you have done, and ſtill do (but for ſuch, we deſire that the Lord would forgive you, and ſhew you what you do) but not to convince us by ſound Doctrine, but by the Inſtruments of fooliſh Shepherds do you war againſt us, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h as they uſe whom you your ſelves account <hi>Anti chriſtian,</hi> as well as we; for ſuch that think the Way to ſave Souls, is to afflict, puniſh and kill the Body, have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Truth, as it is in Jeſus, nor the ſound Wiſdom from above, <hi>Which is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be entreated, full of Mercy and good Fruits; for the Fruit of Righteouſneſs is ſown in Peace</hi> mark that but the Fruit of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs is ſown in Fightings, Beatings, Stockings, Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Baniſhings, Impriſonings, Finings, Robbing and Spoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Goods, deſtroying of Families, by making many Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and Fatherleſs-Children: Is this the Way to bring Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the Kingdom of God? then the Apoſtles were much miſtaken; for they never made Uſe of this Way, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; for theſe Things were u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed againſt them by thoſe that knew not God; but thoſe that have received the Spirit of Chriſt (are Chriſt's) and know the Apoſtles were not miſtaken; but it is you that are miſtaken in ſuffering the Spirit of the World to bear Rule in you, and that take to it the Honours and Preferments of the World, that are but Temporal, and ſo in the World are Lords many, but in the Church of Chriſt one God and one Lord, the great Shepherd and Biſhop of his Soul, who gives many Biſhops or Overſeers, but no Lords, as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43044:10"/>the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>But to us there is but one God, the Father, of whom are all things, and we in him; and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom are all Things, and we by him,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.6. And thoſe who are by him now gathered out of the World (that lyeth in VVickedneſs) and have received the Spirit of Truth, cannot but ſtand Witneſſes againſt thoſe that are of the World who receive and give Honour one to another, and would be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſent of God, to rule in <hi>his Houſe, which is the Church of the Living God,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.15. But ſuch manifeſt themſelves by taking the World that lyeth in Wickedneſs, to be the Church, the Houſe of God, and ſo make all the Nation to be of their Church, except ſuch they have caſt out, which for the moſt Part are ſuch that are gathered of Chriſt out of the World; So that all the Thieves, Murderers, VVhore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, Adulterers, Whores, Drunkards, Swearers, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, Lyars, and all People of all Sorts, that will hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and pay you, both <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and all Sects and Sorts, you account are of your Church, except ſuch you caſt out, as I have ſaid, ſo that <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Sodom</hi> and all is here by you taken to be the Church of Chriſt, the Houſe of God; what a Houſe have you provided for the living God to dwel in the midſt of? What a Church is here? Is this <hi>the Pillar and Ground of the Truth?</hi> Do theſe hold the Myſtery of Faith in a pure Conſcience? Or rather, doth not the Myſtery of Iniquity hold them in a defiled One? But if they will hear the Prieſt, and pay him (as I have ſaid) let them believe or hold what they will, all is received of the Church: Oh! what a foul Houſe is here for thoſe you would force to dwell in, who are called out to touch no Unclean Thing? What a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy have you prepared for that glorious Head to be joyned to, that is ſeparate from Sinners, and made higher then the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens? Was not here ſufficient Cauſe for the People ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually gathered to come out from among you? Do you put a Difference between the Precious and the Vile? Yes, you do; for the Precious you curſe out, and deliver to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, though ſome of them were never of you, nor owned you.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:43044:10"/>
               <p>And you have heaped up ſuch a Company of your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Children to reform your Church, who are ſo Zealous for God <hi>Mammon,</hi> that for Non-Payment of a Groat or two, they caſt out a Man, and deliver him to Satan; ſo it ſeems, a Groat or two by them is more prized, then the Soul of a Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yea, or his Body, Life and Family, that they can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them to Priſons, to the ruining of Families; but as to their delivering to Satan, it is paſt their Spiritual Skill in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, who are erred and ſtrayed from the Power of God, which is the Way of God, and that Power gives them Victory over Satan that are turned to it, and ſo their Satan is ſome Goaler, a Member of their own Body; it is like they may be conſcious to themſelves that they have not ſpiritual Power to bind and looſe the Souls of Men; and therefore they will be ſure to bind the Body in ſome naſty Hole or Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but if Money come, then Soul and Body and all ſhall be looſed and bleſt into their Church again, though he be of the worſer Sort to Men.</p>
               <p>Theſe Practices ſavour more of a Synagogue of Satan, then a Church of God; for the Church of God, that abides in the Doctrine of Chriſt, and is a ſweet Savour to God and all Juſt Men that live by Faith; but theſe are a Stink in his Noſtrils, and an Ill Savour to all ſober minded Men, and one of the greateſt Grievances in the Nation, that is to ſay, the <hi>Spiritual Courts,</hi> ſo called, that are yet of the World, and cannot overcome the Fleſh nor the Devil; theſe pretend to caſt People out of that which they were ever in themſelves, to wit, the Church of God: And ſome being caſt out of their Church once, and delivered to Satan (as they pretend) which in Truth is but the delivering of the Body to the Envy and Cruelty of that perſecuting oppreſſing Spirit that dwells in their Adverſaries) and theſe that could never come to them to be reſtored, yet have caſt them out the ſecond Time, and ſome the third, for not coming to their Church, which was contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their own Law: Was ever ſuch Non-ſenſical Work acted by Men pretending to reform the Church? Is not <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeah</hi>'s Prophecy fulfilled upon them, as it was upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they went a whoring from their God, and loved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:43044:11"/>Reward, <hi>The Dayes of Viſitation are come, the Dayes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence are come,</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall know it, the Prophet is a Fool, the Spiritual Man is mad; for the Multitude of thine Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and the great Hatred,</hi> Hoſea 9.7. What Prophets were they that were Fools in <hi>Hoſeah</hi>'s Dayes? thoſe that prophecied, and the Lord never ſent them, who had not received the Word of the Lord, but told the People their Dream for a Reward, upon every Corn fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or; but the true Prophets, that had received the Word, ſpake it or preached it freely, as the Lord ſaid, <hi>He that hath my Word, let him ſpeak my Word freely, what is the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ff to the Wheat?</hi> The Word is the Wheat; the Chaff is what he preacheth that hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Word, that is but the Divination of his own Brain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and theſe were the Fools that had not received the Word of Wiſdom <hi>from above, that is fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt pure, the peaceable;</hi> but the fooliſh Prophets, that propheſied for a Reward, he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnſed to put into their Mouthes, they prepared War againſt them. Were theſe fooliſh and falſe in the Dayes of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and can thoſe that walk in their Steps be true in this Age? Nay, for the Teſtimony of the Spirit of God was againſt ſuch in all Ages, and ſo it is againſt them in this Age: Were they faſſe then that preached or proplie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied, and had not received the Word? ſo they are now: Were they falſe then that propheſied for a Reward in every Corn-floor? and are they not ſo now, that preach for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in every Corn-field? Was the falſe Prophet then as <hi>the Snare of a Fowler in all his Wayes, and Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed againſt the Houſe of his God?</hi> and is he not ſo now? All that have eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Snare know, the Lord hath delivered them out of the Mouthes of the falſe Shepherds, according to his Premiſe, and hath exalted the Mountain of his Houſe above their Mountains, and above all Hills, and thither he hath gathered, and is gathering his People in this Nation, and will gather them in all Nations into this Houſe of the Lord, where there is Bread enough; and the falſe Prophets, and fooliſh blind Prieſts in this Age, are in Hatred againſt this Houſe of the Lord of Hoſts, and againſt the Gatherings of his People in it, and the Flewings together of the Nations unto it, according to the Word of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43044:11"/>Lord; but the Work of the Lord doth proſper, and will proſper, and all Oppoſers of it (except they repent) will periſh; for the falſe Shepherds ſhall howl, and their Paſtere ſhall be ſpoiled, For you have deſpiſed and rejected the Counſel of the great Shepherd and Biſhop of the Soul, and are Oppoſers of the Work of his Spirit in his People, who have received the Truth, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, <hi>And if any Man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith; and thoſe that walk in the Obedience of the Meaſure of his Spirit, you have hated and perſecuted; and ſome of you being fill'd with Envy againſt them, have turned informers, like <hi>Judas,</hi> that informed againſt Chriſt for Money; after he had betrayed the Truth in himſelf, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil entered, and fitted him with Envy, to come againſt Chriſt and his Diſciples, where they were aſſembled, to betray them into the Hands of their Enemies; and hath not Envy filled ſome of your Hearts, and ſo fitted you to inform againſt the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies gathered in the Name and Spirit of Chriſt, as ſome of you have done, and have ſworn againſt them; and one confeſt before the Magiſtrate, that he did not know that ever he had ſeen ſome of their Faces before, and yet ſome time before had ſworn they were at the Meeting; but all muſt be conſtrued for the Purpoſe, that is to ſpoil the Goods of thoſe that cannot forſake the aſſembling of themſelves together in the <hi>true Worſhip</hi> of God.</p>
               <p>And ſome of you have procured Warrants to ſpoil the Goods of your Neighbours, and ſome have ſpoiled them over and over, and proſecuted thoſe that would not ſpoil them: Is this the Way to teach the People to <hi>Love their Neighbours as themſelves, and to do to all People as they would be done unto?</hi> this is the Way indeed to manifeſt what Spirit you are of; and ſo People may read your Father's Name in your Forehead's, whoſe Works do you do, what Spirit leads you, whether the Spirit of <hi>Cain</hi> that wicked One, or the Spirit of <hi>Abel</hi> the Righteous One? by your Fruits you are known: Doth the Work of this Spirit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that Chriſt is come in your Fleſh, that Righteous One; or Anti-chriſt, that Wicked One, whom Chriſt is <hi>Conſuming with Breath of his Mouth, and the Brightneſs of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oming?</hi> Was it ever known that a Miniſter of Chriſt was an Informer againſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Meetings? no, it never was, nor ever will be; for ſuch
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43044:12"/>are not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, but in the Practice of thoſe the Scripture calls <hi>Wolves in Sheeps Cloathing;</hi> but in this Work of Informing, the Wolf only appears, that comes to devour; ſo that Spirit that preacheth for Hire, is the ſame that ſpoils Men's Goods for Hire; and he that takes Wages of Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, doth the Work of Unrighteouſneſs; Did not thoſe that devoured Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dows Houſes, do the Work of Unrighteouſneſs, though for a Pretence made long Prayers? and thoſe were Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Chriſt then, and can they be Friends now? no, ſuch are an ill Savour to God, and a Stink in his Noſtrils; what have ſuch to do to take his Name into their Mouthes who hate to be reformed by his Spirit, and perſecute thoſe that are? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Souls are you guilty of the Blood of? And how many Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies have you caſt into Priſon till Death? How many Widdows and Fatherleſs Children have you made in this Nation, becauſe they could not put into your Mouthes, knowing what Spirit you were of; and that the Lord never ſent you, as by your Fruits you have manifeſted to the View of the Nation? and Thouſands ſee you, and will buy your Merchandize no more; and if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not compel them by your Law, then you make Merchandize and Spoil of their Goods.</p>
               <p>But Wo is unto you, that ever you were born, becauſe of the terrible Day that is coming upon you, which you can no wayes eſcape, but by coming out of her, in whom is found all the Blood of the Saints and Martyrs, and all that have been ſlain (for the Teſtimony of Jeſus) upon the Earth.</p>
               <p>For now the Everlaſting Goſpel is preaching, that ſhall be preached to all Nations, Tongues and Languages, for the gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to their Light, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the Hope of their Glory: <hi>For to him ſhall the Gathering of the People be, and the</hi> Gentiles <hi>ſhall walk in thy Light, and Kings in the Brightneſs of thy Riſing; then thou ſhall ſee and ſhine, thy Heart ſhall be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and enlarged, becauſe the Multitude of the Sea ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted unto thee, and the Riches of the</hi> Gentiles <hi>ſhall come unto thee,</hi> Iſa. 60.3.5. <hi>For the Lord ſhall be thy Everlaſting Light, and thy God thy Glory,</hi> Ver. 19. <hi>Thy People alſo ſhall be all Righteous, they ſhall poſſeſs the Land forever; the Graft of my planting ſhall be the Work of mine Hands, that I may be glorified; a little One
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43044:12"/>ſhall become a Thouſand, and a ſmall One as a ſtrong Nation, I the Lord will haſten it in due Time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> propheſied of, that ſhould be <hi>a Burthenſom Stone unto all Nations</hi> (which is become a burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Stone in this Nation) <hi>but all that burthen themſelves with it ſhall be broken in Pieces by it;</hi> and how many have been bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in Pieces by it, that oppoſed it in this Nation? and all that yet ſhall oppoſe it in this or any other Nation, ſhall be broken in Pieces and confounded by it, except they repent and be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered into it; for God is making his little One to become a Thouſand, and his ſmall One a ſtrong Nation; and theſe are his holy Nation, and peculiar People, and ſpiritual Prieſthood, that are gathered out of the Fleſh, where none can pleaſe God, into the Spirit of his Son, where all walking do pleaſe him; and theſe cannot pleaſe Men; for the Gift that God hath given (that Man is to receive if he pleaſe God) the VViſdom of the Fleſh did alwayes reject in all Ages, and ſo it doth in this; and it was a <hi>ſtumbling Stone and a Rock of Offence</hi> to the VViſe and Prudent of this World among the <hi>Jews</hi> in that Age, <hi>diſallowed of Men, but choſen of God, elect and precious</hi> to thoſe that believe, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> in all Ages, <hi>a tryed Corner-Stone,</hi> the Power of God to all thoſe that receive it, who through Obedience of it become the Sons and Daughters of God.</p>
               <p>And now I warn all in this Nation that profeſs <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> to conſider your Wayes, whether you are entered in at the ſtraight Gate, and whether you walk in the narrow VVay, that only leads to Life; for out of it there is no Salvation: And God is riſen to overturn every falſe VVay in this the Day of his Power, in which the VVay of the VVicked ſhall be turned upſide down, but the VVay of the Lord ſhall be exalted, which as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Is the New and Living Way,</hi> the New Covenant of Light to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that is <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Hope of Glory, which is Chriſt the Spirit of Truth and VVord of Life in Man, that whoſoever receives and walks in, is of God, and come out of the VVorld; but he that receives it not, is not paſt from Darkneſs, but is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of it, in the VVorld that lyeth in VVickedneſs, where God is not pleaſed; but as many as have received the VVord in their Hearts, and in it believe, are grafted by Faith into Chriſt, the Root, the Vine and Power of Life, the incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43044:13"/>Seed, <hi>the Word of God that liveth and abideth for ever,</hi> and becauſe he liveth, all in him are made alive to God again; and theſe walk in him, that is, his Spirit, that God the Father hath given to lead them into all Truth (and out of him none can pleaſe God, nor walk in his Truth) and theſe be his Diſciples in this Age, that have received him the VVord, and for the Obedience of him the World hates them, as it doth him, and now perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes him in his Members, as he ſaid they would, and we witneſs his Word fulfilled in us; but in his Spirit we have Victory over the World and their Spirit, becauſe he that we have received (the Word, the Spirit of Truth) <hi>in us, is greater then he that is in in the World;</hi> and that Spirit that is in the World is now making <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar againſt the Spirit which we have received, and is in us that are not of the World: And here is the Lamb's War againſt the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet: And as ſure as <hi>John</hi> ſaw the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet overcome, taken alive, and caſt into the Lake of Fire, ſo ſure ſhall we overcome in his Spirit, that hath overcome in his own Body the World, the Fleſh and the Devil, and now is revealed in us to overcome for us, in whom we have good Comfort, and in the Faith ſee that Spirit that makes War againſt us (in Prieſts and Profeſſors, and all perſecuting Rulers and Magiſtrates) ſhall be overcome; and all that come not out of that Spirit, but continue in it, in the Hatred and War to the End, will be caſt into the Lake of <hi>Fire,</hi> as <hi>John</hi> ſaw in the Revelation of the Spirit of Truth that cannotlye.</p>
               <p>Therefore I warn you all, to hear the Voice of the Spirit of Truth that calls to you from Heaven to come out of her, in whom all the Blood is found, that is, that Spirit that perſecuted the Church of God in all Ages, the Spirit of the World that rules in the Children of Diſobedience, that is he that is in the World, and the World are in it that is, all that have not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Spirit of Chriſt, are they that are none of his; but they that have received his Spirit, are they that the World hates, as he ſaid it ſhould be; for as he is not of the World, ſo all in him (that is, his Spirit) are not of the World.</p>
               <p>And now let all conſider what Spirit they are joyned to; <hi>For they that are joyned to the Lord are one Spirit; but they that are joyned to the Harlot</hi> (the Falſe Spirit, or Falſe Prophet) <hi>are one Body,</hi> whatever they do profeſs for a Religion it matters not;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43044:13"/>for Hypocrites in all Ages were ſuch that ſaid, and did not, and ſo they are now, that call themſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and are not in Chriſt's Spirit; for as ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>If any Man ſay he is in him, he ought himſelf to walk even as he walked;</hi> and he that is not in Chriſt's Spirit is no <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> but profeſſing Chriſt's Life, and living after the Fleſh, is in Hypocrifie; and the Life of Chriſt in his People judgeth that, and condemns that Religion, and declares that Life to be <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian,</hi> and but the Birth of the Fleſh, that perſecutes him that is born of the Spirit; and though that Birth by its great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion may have a Name to live, and be perſecuted for its Name, yet having not the Nature of Chriſt to be its Life, cannot hold out to the Death, but muſt give Way, and flee before their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies into Holes and Corners, becauſe they are not come to the Power of God in themſelves, that is <hi>he that is greater then he that is in the World:</hi> And therefore all you great Profeſſors that are againſt the Light of Chriſt in you, in which <hi>Power is received to become the Sons of God, and over come the World,</hi> you are overcome by him that is in the VVorld, and he <hi>makes you leave your great licenſed Meeting houſes to the Bats and the Owls, that love the Light Natural no more then you do the Spiritual,</hi> as of late in many Places you have done; <hi>and ſo your Gatherings in the Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of your own Brains, come to be ſcattered according to the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of your Enemies, who have not therein imagined a vain or ineffectual Thing againſt you, but they ſee they have againſt thoſe that the Lord gathered out of Darkneſs into his marvelous Light:</hi> But if you were not blind, you might ſee that <hi>you are not gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Name, that is, the Power of God, the Rock that God built his Church upon in all Ages, that the Gates of Hell might not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt them:</hi> Cannot you ſee what Power it is that ſcatters you, what Spirit and Power is it that leads the Informers, which for the moſt Part are the wickedeſt of Men? <hi>Is it not he that led</hi> Judas <hi>the Informer, whem the Rulers paid, and the Devil ſet at Work? and you in your</hi> Anti-chriſtian <hi>Prudence flee before;</hi> for <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prudence leads to do that which is given of Chriſt to do; <hi>for as it is given to believe, ſo alſo to ſuffer for his ſake,</hi> in whom we have believed: <hi>But where the Gift of God is not received, there true Faith is not witneſſed, but Fleſh and Blood is conſulted withal, that never led to do the Will of God; but he that ſuffered himſelf,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43044:14"/>and in it did the Will of God, is the Leader of all his that ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake; for they that will not ſuffer with him, cannes reign with him over that Spirit that makes War againſt him, which is to be conquered by Suffering;</hi> for that Spirit that leads to decline a publick Teſtimony, and to flee from Suffering &amp; Perſecution for Righteouſneſs ſake, is one with that Spirit which perſecutes; for that Spirit that leads to perſecute the Children of Truth, can never lead to ſuffer for the Truth; for it is out of it: <hi>So that it is clear, that Spirit that leads to run from Perſecution, when they have Power, will lead them to perſecute, as in</hi> New-England <hi>doth appear, by ſuch who could not ſuffer for their Religion, but joyned to the Power of Darkneſs, and perſecuted to Death the Children of Light that could; ſo they have conquered that Spirit, and their Life doth tread that Religion under Foot; for its but</hi> Cain<hi>'s Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, without Faith that worketh by Love, which the Spirit of the Lord loathes, being in that Spirit that ſlew his Brother, in which they preached, that ſhall be aſhamed of their Goſpel, not being the Power of God to Salvation; for if it were, they that hear, and they that preach it would not flee before the Power of Satan; but where he that ſaves the Soul is not received, he that kills the Body will be feared; and ſo the Counſel of Chriſt being rejected, his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comes to be tranſgreſſed; and thus the Wind that purifies and winnows the Wheat, blows the Chaff unto the Dunghil: So they that cannot ſtand in Time of Tryal, declare themſelves to be but Chaff, that the Wind blows too and fro, for if the Waity Life dwell not within, ſuch Mens Religion is but a fooliſh Thing; for he that ſaith,</hi> VVithout me you can do nothing, <hi>is he that is come that all might have Life and Power to do the Will of God, and he that hath received him, hath Life and Power to do the Will of God, and ſo becomes a Child of God; but he that hath him not, hath not Life nor Power to do the Truth, and that Mans Religion is vain: So it is clear, that all thoſe that deny Chriſt, the Light, to be come in Spirit within, are</hi> Anti-chriſtian, <hi>as well as they that denyed him come in the Fleſh, and ſuch are not of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given forth in the Love of him, who would have all Men to be ſaved, and to come unto the Knowledge of the Truth
<date>
                        <hi>This</hi> 3d <hi>of the</hi> 2d <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1675.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>M. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prophecy">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:43044:14"/>
            <head>The Prophecy of <hi>John Hus;</hi> Propheſying of the Reformation of the <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Church</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>cannot be reduced to her former Dignity and reformed, before all Things firſt be made new, the Truth whereof appeareth by the Temple of</hi> Solomon, <hi>as well the Clerks and Prieſts, as alſo the People and Laity; or elſe except all ſuch as now be addicted to Avarice, from the leaſt to the moſt, be firſt converted and renewed, as well the People, as the Clerks and Prieſts, Things cannot be reformed. Albeit, as my Mind now giveth me, I believe rather the firſt, that is, that then ſhall riſe a New People, formed after the New Man, which is created after God; of the which People New Clerks and Prieſts ſhall come forth and be taken, who all ſhall hate Covetouſneſs and Glory of this Life, labouring to an Heavenly Converſation; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all theſe Things ſhall be done and wrought in Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Order of Time, diſpenced of God for the ſame Purpoſe; and this God doth, and will do, of his own Goodneſs and Mercy for the Riches of his Patience and Sufferance, giving Time and Space of Repentance to them that have long lain in their Sins, to amend and flee from the Face of the Lord's Fury, until at length all ſhall ſuffer together, and until both the Carnal People, and Prieſts, and Clerks in Proceſs and Order of Time, ſhall fall away, and be conſumed, as is the Cloth conſumed and eaten of the Moth.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
